[Music]
thank you
experience
[Music]
hello and welcome back to the ask
Abhijit show I hope you're all doing
very well it's been a while since we had
this live stream I've been traveling a
lot but here we are I'm back so I hope
you're all very well and thank you very
much for being on this live stream with
me
uh as you know this is a live stream in
which I'm gonna take questions from the
live chat only not from uh questions
asked in the comments so that this is a
more interactive session and you know
there's more interaction and you can ask
questions that I would otherwise maybe
Miss
so that's what we will do tonight and
let's see who all is there on the live
stream I can see Abhishek Sharma Rogue
Gamers
Celestial dust Suraj
Sunny Imran
Abhishek Rogue gamer anupam
Adele kodzer
Aditya DK boss
foreign
[Music]
and lots and lots of other people it's
good to see you all thank you so much I
for being here I will not be able to
greet you all individually but but yes
greetings
so with that done let's get into the
questions if you have questions start
asking me now and I'll take as many as I
can from the live stream from the live
chat so let's see what do we have
let us see what do we have kalpana says
why didn't our Kings do anything to save
nalanda University even if the universe
was burned why was it not restored later
I am sure our Kings must have tried to
resist the Turks you know uh what's what
was the name was the Barbarian who
destroyed the the University
so he was able to do this because he was
he was able to defeat the king whoever
it was who you know ruled that area so
the king must have resisted
Indian Kings must have resisted the
problem was that it was not that we did
not resist the problem was lack of
political Unity at that time
you see Indian history is is full of
these cycles in which you have political
Unity under a single Empire and then the
Empire eventually dissolves and then you
have fragmentation lots of little
kingdoms you know and when you have
little kingdoms they are all competing
against each other and that's what you
we call lack of unity so instead of
working together or having a single
leadership they're gonna be you know
disunited and that's when it's easy for
Outsiders to come in and do whatever
they do you know plunder pillage invade
conquer occupy that's what they do so
our Kings resisted we have this you know
our education system our history books
our teachers have created this
impression that uh our Kings did not do
anything which is completely wrong our
Kings resisted fiercely for centuries
but eventually we know what happened so
the process of the conquest of India by
the Turks that process took at least
three or four centuries and they were
never able able to conquer the entire
subcontinent entirely so
the other thing so
our things resisted but eventually
um the the bhaktir khilji was able to
conquer that area Eastern India
and Bihar what we call Bihar now and
they destroyed the university and we see
we are witnessing similar scenes in
France right now
and even if the universe was burned why
wasn't why was it not restored later
well you know the the
library in that University burned for
several months so you can imagine how
many books we lost how do you restore
that thousands of years of knowledge and
Records historical records scientific
advancements all of that was burned how
do you restore that
knowledge is precious wisdom is precious
it's it's it's you know recorded on
fragile manuscripts and all that once
that burns it's gone it's it's it's
smoke how do you restore that and yeah
so that's a library what about the
university itself well after that the
Turks ruled the area
and why would they want the university
to be restored it's not like they came
there they plundered they destroyed the
burden then they left no
you know so there are waves upon ways of
turkic invasions and eventually we know
what happened the Bengal Sultan is right
so when you have a Turk ruling Bengal in
in eastern India why would they allow
the university to be restored and
rebuilt won't happen
so you know we had universities great
universities
mahavishnavidyalayas all across the
length and the breadth of India and none
of them exists today
so you know we were not allowed our
ancestors were not allowed to rebuild
these universities so this is you know a
cautionary tale for us we have to learn
from our history we can never allow this
to happen again
and for that we need political Unity
even today India is this United even
today Indians are fighting each other
you see this all the time on social
media sniping at each other and saying
you are wrong I am wrong I'm right
you're wrong fighting each other even
today
the dominant identity for most Indians
is the sub-national identity my region
my state my language
and they identify by that first they
identify with that first not as Indians
I may be Indian but I am this or I am
that I speak this language I'm from this
region I have this this religion maybe
foreign religions or whatever and just
keep on fighting fighting fighting
fighting each other this is the problem
we still have this problem
and we also have this federal system
federalism which makes India so
internally weak all the energy is spent
fighting inside you know so that's the
issue so we still have um much to learn
and much to change the system that has
been imposed upon us this parliamentary
democracy system is not ideal for India
they need a better system I'm not saying
we need to reject democracy we need to
have a better democratic system we are
the inventors of democracy to sort of
say democracy was it first emerged out
of India so anyway that's the deal and
uh yeah that's the answer to that
question in brief
um
Melvin says what do you think about
Peter zehan's assessment on India not
becoming a major power because with many
internal problems is it true from his
perspective from his point well I have
not read what he has written or said I
have not heard what he has said but okay
so in case he I'm aware of the guy he is
a geopolitical analyst he has written a
few books I suppose I expect I believe
at least one I don't remember the name
but anyhow so
assuming that he has made the assessment
that India will not become a major power
because of its many internal problems
there is some truth to that
see Indians keep asking about when are
we going to become a superpower I would
say forget about being a superpower or a
vishwa guru
try to become a reasonably like
semi-developed Nation first
you can't
Sprint before you learn how to walk and
we are still learning how to walk so
like I just said about the previous
question we have so many internal
problems it's true
we are so disunited
there is so much you know this
subnational identities that we have in
India every State's every state in India
fights the other certain states have
political parties that espouse you know
soft separatist ideology
the the Aryan Innovation theory has
created this deep divide between the
so-called dravidians and the so-called
Aryans
which is completely fictitious it's the
Aryan tourism Theory or the RN picnic
Theory now but whatever
but people have internalized these these
fake ideas you know because and because
we are still taught this nonsense
so the first thing that needs to happen
is we need to change the education
system improve it
you know so none of this is being
addressed right now we have what the new
education policy which is like you know
putting
um
putting Band-Aid on a gunshot wound on a
bullet wound that's the kind of thing it
is it does nothing it doesn't address
the real issues so uh yeah we have lots
of internal problems but I'm sure you
know
the biggest problems you know when you
have very complicated issues you we need
some Simple Solutions the more
complicated a problem is the simpler the
solution has to be
so that's a good thing
yeah but it will take you know political
will to change things I think India will
eventually become a major power I think
India is the only nation in in the next
20 years that's posing major nation
whose economy is going to keep growing
so I think you know we do have problems
but we do have uh uh strong points as
well and as long as we keep electing the
right leaders we're going to eventually
be fine I think it's a matter of time
maybe in the next 10 20 years we may
even have a new constitution you know
things may change that much right now
this this decade the 2020s it's a very
it's a time of very uh rapid and
significant geopolitical change change
that you typically see happen over
decades we are seeing it happen over
years
so things could change significantly and
so I don't entirely agree with Peter
zehan's assessment that India will not
become a major power in India does have
major problems major internal problems
but those can be solved with with
political will so as long as we keep
electing the right leaders
then eventually you know they're going
to chip away the problems and eventually
there'll be a Tipping Point when the
solutions will come much faster
so if Peter zahan has made his an
assessment that India will not become a
major power I think I I disagree with
that very strongly India will become a
major power nobody can stop us
all right
now let us see
um
let's see some of the questions
Anish says could you please create a
documentary style video on the Manipur
matter to help clarify misconceptions
you know I've stayed away from the
Manipur matter because it's an ongoing
crisis it's an ongoing issue it's a very
sensitive matter I I
and you know
whenever something new happens
experts crop up
so when galwan happened all of a sudden
you had all these China experts who
popped up who cropped up everybody
became a China expert
when Ukraine happened everybody became a
Russia and Ukraine expert when the
Titanic submarine sank or whatever
happened everybody became a submarine
expert and now everybody is becoming a
Manipur expert
you know we need to be very careful not
to believe everything that these
so-called experts tell us on social
media and and you know journalists and
all that the matter is very complicated
it has historical roots that go back at
least a century if not three centuries
uh and this is an ongoing issue so I
have deliberately and consciously
decided not to speak about this right
now
it's a very complex issue and there are
certain things that will open up entire
Pandora's boxes
you know certain issues that I think I
should not speak about right now so
that's why I have consciously and
deliberately not spoken about this maybe
eventually I'll make a video maybe
eventually I'll invite a guest who is a
you know a recognized expert on the
matter
and have them speak about this
or maybe I will deal with this only from
a geopolitical perspective so I think
eventually I will do it but right now
it's it's a very sensitive matter that's
all I can say so I would prefer not to
speak too much about this right now
but yeah it's it's a
it's it's a terrible situation
and it's geopolitical matter you know
people see only The Superficial surface
level stuff of what's happening and
they'll say that nothing is being done
but you know
uh like I said it's a complicated matter
it's actually a geopolitical issue there
are outside forces that are that are
have making this happen the same way
that what's happening in France to some
extent has external you know has an
external hand as well much of it is
France's own fault but there is an
external hand as well in this so
something similar is happening in
Manipur
you know all these terrorists who are
terrorizing the natives of Manipur how
who is organizing them all who is
providing them the leadership and the
coordination who is providing the funds
you know these questions have to be
asked and the uh spontaneous movements
don't arise spontaneously you need
leadership you need uh cohesion you need
organization you need leadership and you
need funding where is it all coming from
so there's a whole lot that's happening
right now I just hope that things will
simmer down peacefully and I hope it's
not only peace that is imposed but
Justice that is given and the terrorists
and the foreigners who have infiltrated
in large numbers are evicted that's what
needs to happen we have we are a nation
of compromises we keep compromising we
are a nation of low standards we allow
anybody to come into India and settle
down and start claiming rights and all
that we need to raise our standards like
I keep saying on this on this show we
need to raise our standards right now we
are a nation of low standards we keep
compromising with uh intolerant people
we need to we need to crack down a
little bit anyhow that's the deal
they just says why is France
falling
why are there more and more civil wars
in Europe
good question now this is something I
can speak about a little more openly uh
okay so what's happened what's the deal
with France right now we know uh France
is burning
uh Paris is burning lots of other cities
you have like wide scale rioting
happening
you have individuals with automatic
weapons who are firing
there is a vandalism there's arson I
don't know what people I don't know if
anyone's you know you've had casualties
or not but yeah so
apparently some immigrant
male 17 years old was was asked by the
police to stop and the guy did not
listen to the cops and he tried to drive
off in the shot him
so this is standard practice in the West
if a cop tells you to do something you
got to obey if you don't obey they can
shoot you
that's just how it is in the west so and
this individual this boy whoever he was
did not listen to the cops so he got
shot
and yeah he happened to be uh you know
not an adult he was 17. there are so
many things that happen you know
but there is no outage about that
I mean these so-called immigrants or
whoever they have been doing all kinds
of crimes
against the natives and none of that you
know evokes any outrage
but this issue suddenly it it created
this spontaneous Outburst of rioting all
across the length and the breadth of
France this is nonsense this is clearly
something that's coordinated and
orchestrated now from where is it
happening I don't know but I would not
say that France is not to blame they
have allowed so many so many immigrants
into their Nation at least
I don't know if you look at the total
population of France I would say 10 to
20 percent would be immigrants now and
these people have never assimilated they
first of all never been allowed to
assimilate properly they have always
been treated as second-class Citizens
there's a lot of racism okay so France
is not blameless entirely
they have this terrible Legacy of
colonialism in North Africa in Algeria
and other places parts of other parts of
Africa
uh they did all kinds of brutalities and
all that they are still
actively engaged in neocolonization in
large parts of Africa the French okay so
they are not blameless
and lots of these immigrants lots of
these people from the former French
colonies and other parts of Africa have
settled in France lots of North Africans
algerians Etc
and they
are kind of marginalized so they do feel
disenfranchised they do feel like the
French don't treat them as like they are
also Supreme citizens even second
generation third generation immigrants
they still feel you know like Outsiders
there is this angst there is this anger
the economic situation is not the same
it's it's quite different there are
these paths there are these suburbs in
Paris the bonus where these which are
like ghetto-like places there is crime
there are parts of Paris where the cops
can't go
yeah it sounds similar to what you some
other things that you may have
experienced yes
there are parts of Paris where the where
the cops simply cannot go there are drug
lords and so much happening there is so
much crime hidden below the surface in
France in Paris Paris is this great
tourist destination well there are
certain parts of Paris which are
definitely not tourist destinations you
can visit the Champions the the Eiffel
Tower and whatever it is whatever else
but yeah so
so that's the deal you know so that's
the background to what's happening now
so this one immigrant was shot I mean
maybe he was born there I'm not sure
what his life history is not not
important this fellow was shot and then
there was a spontaneous apparently
Outburst of rioting all across France
which you know which is unnatural
when you have so many incidents of
writing happening at the same time they
all start at the same time
it's clearly something that's
coordinated so who's coordinating this
who's providing the hidden leadership
who's providing the funding that's the
question now we have to understand this
is not only something that's happening
in France we are seeing this all across
Europe Belgium is another issue Belgium
also has lots of Arabs and all kinds of
immigrants Germany has terrible issues
and these people these nations have been
importing
boatloads and truckloads and busloads
and God knows what else loads of
immigrants typically from the Middle
East typically military age males you
know they call them refugees you know
what refugees look like refugees are
helpless people refugees are women and
children mostly but these so-called
refugees who are being imported into
these nations are all young military age
males
who come without their families without
any women and children
what's happening it's unnatural it's
artificial so why are nations like
Germany and and Italy and other nations
European nations why are they
absorbing why are they importing so many
military age uh immigrants why and that
too from only from the Middle East from
the Nations that the Americans bomb and
destroy and then these nations uh become
you know the origin Originators of all
these immigrants and refugees what's
happening
so we have to understand that Europe is
colonized by The Americans the true
power in Western Europe the only Power
the only real power in Western Europe is
the United States
they dictate terms to all the European
nations and there are several European
nations that are still under permanent
U.S military occupation Italy is one
Germany is another
Italy and Germany then this begins when
did this begin 1945 end of the second
world war Italy was defeated Germany was
defeated these were the exports along
with Japan Japan is also entrepreneur
and U.S military occupation so you if
you if you go to the maps okay we have
Maps somewhere let's go to Maps we yes
yes we we have to see the map right
is one of the most important things so
let's go to Italy
and let us go to where shall we go shall
we go to
I don't remember where I was supposed to
go is it Palermo is it cagliari Sardinia
I don't remember
but the point is if you know where to
look you will find U.S military bases
all across Europe and when it comes to
Italy and Germany these are permanent
military bases which means these nations
are under permanent U.S military
occupation the UK is a U.S vasala
you know the UK became a proper U.S
Hotel during the Tony Blair Prime
ministership he was called Tony Blair
was was regarded as George W Bush's
poodle pet poodle it's a very uh harsh
thing to say about somebody but it's not
inaccurate
so the UK is a USB they do whatever the
Americans tell them
Germany has no option but to do what the
Americans tell them they are under
permanent U.S military occupation they
cannot say no to the Americans and you
know there are certain nations in Europe
whose constitutions were either directly
or indirectly written by The Americans
or written by their own people who were
puppets of the Americans because it all
happened with the American set of veto
on the writing of these constitutions
Germany is one Italy is another
and the Japanese Constitution as we know
was entirely written in 1945 by the
Americans and not a word has changed so
France France and and the EU Nations and
Nate the NATO nations are essentially
all under the thumb or under the boats
of the US and what's really happening is
the Americans are forcing these nations
I that's what it looks like to absorb
military age male refugees from the
war-torn Middle East from the Nations
that the Americans have bombed to dust
and by doing so they are destabilizing
Europe why would they destabilize Europe
well Europe in the long run is a threat
to the Americans Germany has always been
a major power in the last century and a
half ever since Otto from Bismarck
unified Germany
right Germany is a long-term threat from
the American perspective if Germany
rises again it's a problem we don't want
a new Reich right coming out of Germany
so
why not destabilize Germany why not
create a disaster demographic disaster
in these nations
so that's what they're trying to do the
destroying of the Nord stream pipeline
allegedly by America allegedly you know
that also serves to destabilize Germany
and create a recession in Germany and
Germany has now entered a recession
so all these so suppose you know all
these disturbances Civil War like
situations these nations they are being
forced to absorb refugees even the
Nordic Nations like Sweden Norway
Denmark Etc they're absorbing bucket
loads truckloads boatloads whatever
loads of refugees of immigrants who have
no desire to assimilate
you know when somebody goes to start a
new life in a new country you're
supposed to respect the local culture
and try to assimilate into the local
population learn the language learn
those lifestyle way of life learn the
um customs and all that and respect that
you have to become one of them but these
immigrants who come there have no desire
to do that they want to impose their own
way of life
on these European nations and that's
being done by Design
so you know all these refugees right now
they're coming into Italy lots of them
came to Germany all of that is being
this is this is you know
uh social re-engineering of these
uh societies I think it's all being done
by the US I mean there's no real
evidence but it all all these immigrants
come from the Nations that the Americans
have bombed to dust it's either Iraq or
Syria or Afghanistan and sometimes there
are lots of pakistanis who come there
because you know Pakistan who wants to
live in Pakistan you know and sadly yeah
so that's what's happening
and I see more of this happening now I
don't see this uh slowing down I I
expect more of this to happen Belgium
you had you know these though remember
the terrible airport Bomb Blast
bomb attack on the airport a few years
ago uh so yeah that issue is there in
Belgium as well so all these European
nations are what's the right word they
are there
not doomed but they are they're going
towards the Doom unfortunately
all right all right all right all right
let's see
uh what other questions do we have
uh Mateo Perez says refugees is great
for population growth which helps with
pension payouts for European countries
they help pay the taxes
does Europe need population growth
and you know uh pension payouts for
European countries well who's from where
is that
let's say you have a refugee a new
Refugee who is newly minted Refugee who
has come to let's say Belgium now this
person is he has no money he's a young
guy he has no money he has no he doesn't
know the local language it's going to
take him let's say six months to learn
the local language and all he can do is
construction work or something and maybe
there isn't even that available right
now so then the government has to
support this guy so where does the money
come from it comes from the taxpayer
right
so it actually is a burden on the host
nation and do these nations need
population growth
I know the birth rates are dropping and
all but I mean it's it's not the right
way to to you know stabilize your
population or make a population grow the
U.S also absorbs immigrants but those
are not refugees they have a very strict
screening procedure was I wrong yeah
after the Biden Administration came into
place they've essentially opened up the
southern border the Texas and all that
border and God knows who all is coming
in they are trying to re-engineer the
demographics of the us as well so yeah
so it's it's a mess it's an absolute
mess that's that's all I can say about
this you know it's an absolute mess and
there's a lesson for us to learn
in India we have to
have standards you can't just allow
anybody to come into India and you know
start claiming rights and citizenship
and all that which is kind of what's
happening right now
uh Lots we know the situation with
Bangladesh don't we
borders borders open borders we have the
BSF on the borders but we know
well let's let's not open that Pandora's
box of the BSF in Bengal
so I think millions of bangladeshis have
poured into India they're all across
India now in all the major cities I
don't know how many rohingyas were
settled into India these are the
standards our governments have had in
the past
and we know the situation in Manipur
lacks of Burmese cookies have poured
into Manipur in the past few decades
they were settled by the Indian
government in the 1950s 60s 70s and then
the last few years also apparently all
of this has happened so we need to raise
our standards we can't just allow
anybody to come into India and start
claiming citizenship we need to learn
from what's happening in Europe
all right
uh let's see what other questions we
have
um
let's see
dictionary says why
have so many Buddha statues being
excavated from Kerala did Buddhism get
suppressed you know Indian history is
thousands of years long Buddhism the
Lord Buddha Gotham Buddha was he lived
apparently as far as we know two and a
half thousand years ago and there was an
entire phase of Buddhism in India when
both the Dharma that particular flavor
of Dharma became the dominant brand of
Dharma in in in India and that was of
course engineered by the mauryan
Emperors you know starting from Ashok
one of the greatest Emperors of India
and one of the yeah we know so uh there
was a time in India when almost
everybody practiced what we now call
Buddhism you know that particular flavor
or brand or or
variety of Dharma and then different
times happened and times changed and you
know
and he once again brought
a different flavor or brand or variety
of Dharma to the four so these are
natural events these happen over time
it's not something that that happened
over a week's time it took centuries
so there's no suppression there is this
entire narrative that has been created
you know like I said some time ago there
are so many divisions that have been
created within India artificial
divisions they have separated Buddhism
from Dharma they have separated Jainism
from Dharma yeah so now Buddhism Jainism
Hinduism are three separate religions
apparently and Sikhism also
50 years ago they were it was all part
of Dharma but now we see everything is
separate so whoever is doing this it's
the academics the education system they
are trying to create more and more
divisions within India and they have
created this this narrative that
Buddhism was brutally suppressed by
Hindu Kings by brahmins apparently
this is all nonsense and I don't blame
people for for wondering about this and
asking these questions because this is
what we have been taught this is what
our education system teaches us for like
close to for about two decades of our
life so we absorb this every single day
every single year our teachers keep
telling us this nonsense
maybe they also believe this maybe they
also went through this nonsense
so that's why this narrative has been
created today that Buddhism was
suppressed brutally
which is a lie
which is a lie Society changes over time
Society evolves over time
and before the Advent of the foreign
colonizers like the Turks and the in the
Europeans
It All Happened slowly gradually
naturally organically over centuries
so Buddhism was never suppressed it just
went out of Vogue
it just went out of Vogue over time
right and Buddhism you know what was
this guy's name Alan Watts Alan Watts
said that Buddhism is Hinduism stripped
down for export so it is a truncated and
and and more basic version of Hinduism
which is stripped down for export
because Hinduism is so complex and
complicated but most Outsiders
can't understand it they can't grasp it
so you have to oversimplify it so that
Outsiders can understand it so that's
what Buddhism is
so that's why Buddhism became very
prominent later on in the east east of
India so all the
regions
of Eastern Asia that were once Hindu
eventually became Buddhist so if you
look at the Great temple of Angkor Wat
it was a Vishnu Temple and Buddha is
regarded as an avatar of Vishnu so it
later became a Buddhist temple it's the
largest Hindu temple in the world so it
was you it was a Hindu temple a shaivite
temple but eventually it was used for
Buddhist practice as well and so on you
have so later on China became what we
call Buddhist later on Japan became
Buddhist but if you see Japanese
Buddhism today they worship all the gods
that are that are Hindu gods
you know the worship
kuber the worship Lord Shiva they
worship Ganesha they worship Saraswati
Lakshmi all the gods and goddesses of
Hinduism are part of Japanese Buddhism
so there is no real difference first of
all between Buddhism and Hinduism
the the value system is exactly the same
the morality is exactly the same the
lifestyle is exactly the same but there
are tiny differences you know in the
philosophy in the text and all that and
that's what these tiny two percent or
one person differences are blowed out of
proportion
so it is something that happened
naturally and organically over centuries
Buddhism was never suppressed and there
was a time when much of India practiced
what we call Buddhism so you will find
Buddha statues everywhere in the country
and unfortunately most of the Buddha
statues especially in the northern North
part northern part of India are headless
I wonder why
anyhow
so let's see other questions
um what do we have what do we have
um
let us see what oh I can't snipe says
how did the zoroastrians of Persia
get mostly wiped out of Persia even
though the religion was a one which was
dominant for Millennia and how can how
did Hinduism resist such uh such
terrible events and such a brutal faith
uh Persia is if you look at the map I'm
not sure if people know the map but
let's take a look right
Porsche is present to Iran more or less
you know so historically India was all
the way up to Afghanistan Tajikistan
when chingis Khan the great Khan invaded
uh event on his harassment campaign and
then he entered India at that time the
border of India was at present day
border of Tajikistan and Afghanistan
and west of Afghanistan and Pakistan to
Pakistan temporarily we have Iran which
is Persia
so if you can see Iran is much smaller
than the Indian subcontinent
so and and it's right next to what is
now called Saudi Arabia
so the Arabs were able to invade very
rapidly and they were able to defeat the
Persian Empire rapidly I forget the name
of the last sicinian king you can look
it up
uh
so because Iran was so homogeneous and
much smaller than India and it's very
flat and you know it's it's not that
difficult to
invade and Conquer as you can see it's
there are very few forests and all that
there are mountains zagross mountains
and all but so on so Iran essentially
fell very rapidly and the Arabs who
conquered Iran were able to impose their
faith their religion on the natives
within a matter of a couple of decades
two or three decades
So within two or three decades most
Iranians most Persians had been
converted
to uh the religion of the Arabs
and some of these people they chose not
to give the religion so they fled to
India by sea and they were welcomed in
India and they were given shelter and
refuge and their descendants still live
in India in the still practice
Zoroastrianism and there were some
zerosians who in Iran who refused to
give up the russianism and they were
persecuted very badly and I suppose they
are still persecuted for their faith uh
so that's the thing so their religion
was dominant uh I think let's say 1000
BC is when it starts as we don't quite
know when zarathustra lived but let's
say 1000 BC so
1000 BC to zero so it the the religion
was predominant in Persia for about 1600
1700 years minimum
and then it was white out and where it's
the russianism where did the religion of
zarathustra emerged from it emerged out
of the ancient Vedic religion which was
the predominant religion in in uh
all of India and Persia the portions
were descendants of ancient Indians so
that's the whole thing uh
so that's what happened how did Hinduism
resist this India is much more
complicated much more much larger and
for whatever reason see
Hinduism is a decentralized religion
there is no Pope
there is no head you know it's not a
pyramidal structure of a top-down uh
hierarchy that sort of thing Hinduism is
completely decentralized and that's the
reason why even if they conquered large
parts of India there was no Pope there
was no structure organized structure
there was no coordination so Hinduism
survived wherever it existed
so that is the great strength as well as
a great witness of Hinduism
because of the great because of the
completely decentralized uh structure of
Hinduism Hinduism survived despite the
despite the entire subcontinent coming
under under foreign occupation uh for
about a thousand years of course we know
what happened in Afghanistan the Afghans
were all Hindus and Buddhists and see
what happened is there a single Buddhist
or Hindu alive there today I guess not
if there are any there must be a handful
uh so that's what happened in
Afghanistan we know what happened in
Kashmir but much of India we still have
the the old ancestral culture and
religion that still exists and much of
it exists out of India as well east of
India so so this decentralization that
we have in Hinduism is a great strength
as well as a great weakness it allowed
Hinduism to survive the Thousand Years
roughly of foreign occupation in various
parts of India but it's also something
that you know keeps the people who
follow this Faith they it keeps them
disunited Hinduism is so complex there
are so many different varieties and
flavors of Hinduism that people see that
as you know being different from each
other and you know that that's what
causes problems as well so yeah that's
the deal
um
what's your theory of what was there
before the Big Bang I personally think
the thing was present before the Big
Bang is Brahman was there can you expert
convergent evolution let's talk about
the big bang I don't know what vedanta
says you know
vedanta and The Vedas are not scientific
texts we have our own cosmology of uh
you know
how our our uh ancestors
imagined Evolution to have happened the
evolution of the universe and the time
scales that we have in in Hindu
cosmology are kind of you know the only
time scales that make sense on a
cosmological scale billions of years
maybe trillions of years that sort of
thing uh so in my theory what was there
before the Big Bang I have no theory of
what was there before the Big Bang
because we have no data
all the data that we have is from after
the big bag the so-called Big Bang so I
have no idea whatsoever I can't even
start to speculate about what was there
before the Big Bang
um so yeah listen vedanta is is
spirituality it is religion it is
philosophy
it's religion philosophy spirituality
cannot mix with science you simply
cannot because things these are
completely incompatible and science also
cannot talk about
religion or spirituality or philosophy
so it is completely wrong for a
scientist to to pass opinions about
stuff about things that are not that are
Beyond science and once again in the
same way it is wrong for for people
who who don't have an understanding of
science to pass judgment on science
based on philosophy and spirituality and
religion these things cannot mix
so uh to answer your question in brief I
have absolutely no idea of what was
there before the Big Bang because we
don't have any any data science is all
about data if you have data if you have
then the from on the basis of data you
can make a theory but if you have no
data there can be no Theory there can
only be pure speculation which is
pointless from a scientific perspective
all right let's see some more questions
why don't the Japanese people Abhishek
asks why don't the Japanese people have
any hatred towards the Americans due to
the bombing of Hiroshima and Nagasaki in
World War II
good question
good question and you know Japan is
still under permanent U.S occupation the
Americans have more than 120 or more
than 130 permanent military bases in
Japan
lots of them lots of it is an Okinawa
for example you can look at the map and
find the basis
and so on so forth so why don't the
Japanese hate the Americans well
why don't
why don't Indians hate the British or
the Turks they occupiers and destroyers
of India why it's the same question
it's because of the education system
and the narratives that are created by
the media and the politicians
so in Japan
you have a constitution the Constitution
was written by the Americans in 1945 it
was imposed upon Japan undemocratically
and that's the Constitution that's still
in force not a single word has been
changed
secondly the Japanese education system
is also something that's totally
influenced by the Americans and the
Japanese are taught from day one when
they are three years old or whenever you
start what kindergarten Nursery whatever
they are taught a pacifistic ideology
in the education system and they are
made to believe that the Americans are
great benevolent uh you know people in
the Japan was wrong I'm sure it was
wrong in certain things but whatever
right so uh so it's the education system
that brainwashes people into believing
things
uh and that's essentially what it is
so if you are taught the true history of
what happened you've got to be taught
the correct accurate history Japan did
lots of terrible things in World War II
no doubt about it but I would not agree
that they were entirely completely 100
wrong the their major
where they went wrong is that they lost
so the Americans won and because the
Americans won all of their war crimes
have been whitewashed away Hiroshima and
Nagasaki were nuclear tests on civilians
it's it's I mean how more can you even
be possibly more barbaric and brutal
so because they won all their war crimes
have been covered up and because the
Japanese lost all of their war crimes
have been you know
uh
they they are they're talked about in
they are highlighted and similarly with
with Germany I'm not saying the Germans
were good people I mean the Nazis are
good people obviously they were not good
people they were terrible Hitler was a
monster killed I don't know how many
Jews in Romani gypsies right the Romani
people yeah so so you know war is
complicated geopolitics is complicated
there is no right there is no real right
or wrong
I agree that the Japanese did terrible
war crimes Nanjing is a horrible example
I don't even want to think about Nanjing
what they did in Nanjing uh and other
brutalities in in eastern Asia and all
that
uh but so did the Americans so does
every Empire every Empire indulge is in
brutality every Empire intelligence war
crimes uh
so when it comes to the Japanese people
they are taught from childhood but the
Americans uh did a good thing that the
Americans saved Japan from the from from
its rulers of the of the World War II
era and now Japan is on the right path
Japan is a pacifistic nation they all
believe in pacifism and all that there
is a fringe you know a marginalized
friends in Japan that is nationalistic
but that is frowned upon very strongly
so that's the thing so that's why the
Japanese don't have any hatred towards
the Americans
so that's that's how sheep believe
unfortunately so it's very sad I'm not
saying they should hate anyone but they
should realize that they are under
foreign occupation since 1945 and they
should realize that what happened in
Hiroshima and Nagasaki was brutal
horrific war crimes unforgivable war
crimes but they don't realize it because
that's what the education system has
done to them and that's what actually
you also see in India
that's what's what you see in India as
well yeah anyway
Tibetan pubg player says your opinion on
Tibetan refugees like myself like like
this person over here what's my opinion
I think it's very sad that Tibetans I
have to live outside of their Homeland
Tibet
I think it's very sad what's happening
in Tibet lhasa is a city where you have
ah
well there are more Han Chinese in Tibet
than native Tibetans now right it's
terrible lhasa has discothequez and and
I don't know what bars and casinos and
worse
that's what they did to the holy city of
Lhasa
and they they use Tibet they extract all
the resources out of Tibet the the water
and what whatever else is there so yeah
it's it's sad it's terrible and this is
something that our government India's
government allowed to happen they
allowed the Chinese to do this
they allowed the Chinese to invade and
Conquer Tibet in 19 in the 1950s they
actually it was the great Mr nehru who
was in power at the time the nairobian
regime and the Chinese were starving
because they were so far away from China
they were so badly overstretched so Mr
nehru generously provided lots of rice
to the serving starving Chinese soldiers
and that's how the Chinese are able to
conquer Tibet thanks to the greatest
scenario that's why you you have
Tibetans who are forced to live in Exile
outside of their Homeland and thankfully
the Mr nehru also allowed the Tibetan
refugees to come into India and they
were given shelter in India which is
something that we have always done in
India we have always given shelter to
people who need need shelter
so uh so I think the only place the
Tibetan culture truly survives is now
India and other there are Tibetans in
the west you know other countries as
well but it properly survives only in
India so I I my opinion is that Tibetan
refugees are always welcome you are one
of us you this is your home now for now
at least
eventually uh I hope that Tibet will be
will be free again maybe by 2050
we can make it happen I suppose
if India Rises and then I hope that the
Tibetans who live in India who are born
in India will have the option of staying
in India if they wish or to or going
back to Tibet or maybe being
if Tibet is liberated we could have the
kind of arrangement that we have with
Nepal so India and Nepal are two
separate Nations two separate
administrations but we have an open
Border in Nepalese people do not need a
passport or they don't need a visa to
come to India
they can just cross over and they can
work in India and live in India as long
as they want there are no restrictions
and the same thing applies to Indians as
well and Nepalese are the only uh
people
who are given the uh privilege of
serving in the Indian army so that's the
only other nationality that has given
this privilege and we also have the
notib police right itbp so I think when
Tibet is eventually liberated we will
have we will we will most likely have a
similar kind of arrangement like the one
we have with Nepal an open border and no
restrictions or any of any kind
so I think that happens eventually so
until that happens uh I I think I speak
on behalf of all Indians saying that
Tibetans are welcome in India and
Tibetans uh you know they
they don't have this attitude of other
refugees that we are special and we need
special rights and Privileges and you
need to
the kind of like what we see in Europe
what's happening in France and other
parts of parts of Europe and all that
you know refugees who come in and then
they they
refuse to assimilate
and they try to impose their lifestyle
on the natives but Tibetans have never
done this so that's something I really
appreciate about it because it's the
same culture actually
uh Tibetan culture is
essentially a local very beautiful local
manifestation of Indian culture
it's the same value system the same the
same value is the same philosophy it's
Tibetan Buddhism right so it's the same
culture so there are no cultural clashes
or any such thing
so yeah
so yeah that's my opinion about Tibetan
refugees
all right let's see what else do we have
um
one shuranga says what should I choose
between the Commerce stream and the
child and the science stream I will be
making a decision soon I would
appreciate your opinion well I don't
know you
I appreciate that you asked me this
question but I do not know you
unfortunately personally I do not know
your strengths and your weaknesses
everybody has some strengths and some
weaknesses everybody has
everybody has certain aptitudes
everybody has this unique set of
characteristics I don't know what yours
are so I cannot tell you unless I know
you reasonably well I cannot tell you
what's right for you
so that is a decision a choice that you
have to make yourself we need people in
the Commerce stream we need people in
the science stream as well if you are in
the science stream you can
either become a scientist or a teacher
or a professor or you could go into
business
and and you know into engineering or
something and and do stuff for the
nation or you could become an engineer
or you can start an engineering firm or
or you know
a defense equipment manufacturing firm
or you could go into in the computer
science or whatever so we need people in
the science team but we also need
entrepreneurs and business people
and people who are great at Commerce so
we need both of these all of this is
important
so it's up to you you have to introspect
you know take some time and think about
it what are your strengths what are your
weaknesses what are you good at what are
you not so good at
and where could you in in what capacity
could you best serve Society the best of
the nation and and rise to the fullest
of your potential you have to ask
yourself these questions take some time
to do that and then I suppose I I hope
and you can take the the advice of your
family members your elders your
well-wishers
and then make the decision yourself
so that's what I would tell you without
knowing you I cannot tell you which
stream to take but uh so do this and all
the best
okay let's see what other questions we
have
one shraj bhatti says please shed some
light on the history of the gurijas and
the controversy between the gujars and
the controls between rajputs and gujars
I don't see any controversy this is what
I keep talking about we are so divided
among ourselves rajput versus gujjar and
gujjar versus gurjar and all this
what's the point of all this nonsense I
just don't get it
why are we constantly fighting amongst
each other always some new controversy
it doesn't matter who's what
so historically there was something
called gurjar Desh let's put it on the
map
so what was gurjar Desh we go to Western
India there was historically a region of
India which was called rajputana right
that region came to be known as
rajputana which is presented Rajasthan
and Gujarat
that entire region of Western India was
called rajputana and within rajputana
there was this region called gurjar Desh
all this so Northern
Gujarat and Southern Rajasthan that was
gurjar Desh and the people who lived in
this region were called the gurjars
gurjas could some of them it was a
geographical thing
right
so even a person who belonged to one of
the 32 rajput Clans who lived in
gurjardesh would have been called a
gurjar
now there is something called gujjaras
also which is apparently a different
ethnicity so I I have this podcast this
conversation with virendra Singh rathore
on this channel
in which we have gone into this matter
about the rajput versus gujjar thing
gurjar thing so yeah you can take a look
at that
but my main point is why kid why do we
keep fighting amongst each other it
doesn't matter what your
ancestry is you're Indian
right you've got to work together why do
we just keep on fighting amongst each
other about small little matters that's
what I mean your sub national identity
is more important than your national
identity
and you keep fighting about based on
these things and I don't know who
creates it who foments these fights it's
a constant thing you see and it's it's
tiresome for me
just to feel frustrated when I see
people fighting about these
inconsequential matters it doesn't
matter we all have the same blood
we all have the same DNA you know so we
gotta stop fighting if you take if you
do a DNA analysis of a rajput of a paja
person who has rajput ancestry one of
the 32 or 36 Raj book Clans and a person
who identifies as a gujar or gurjar you
will see no difference
you will see no difference whatsoever
so this is all a waste of time
completely
all right
Krishna says will the dying superpower
USA do any worse in the future oh yeah
when a superpower what's what do you
mean by superpower
superpower is a euphemism for an Empire
so the U.S is a superpower it's also an
Empire it's the largest Empire the world
has ever known and history tells us
that's why I say study history
that's when you will understand
geopolitics if you want if you study
history properly so history tells us
that whenever an Empire starts declining
it lashes out it tries its best to not
disappear
and how do you do that when you become
desperate you start a war you go to war
so the more desperate you are the more
likely you are to go to war
so the US is a declining superpower yes
there's no doubt about it it's declining
it's influence it's declining its power
hasn't declined yet but its influence is
certainly declining
so these are not good science for for a
foreign Empire when it's when people no
longer respect you don't they're no
longer they still
are afraid of you but they don't respect
you anymore today the US has become the
world's laughing stock in a variety of
ways so when a superpower or Empire
declines it lashes out it goes to war so
I think the U.S will engage itself in
many more Wars or start many more many
more wars in the future the major export
see every nation has certain things that
they export right
and the major export of the United
States is war
because it's you know it has this
enormous military industrial complex
that you know manufactures weapons that
designs and develops and manufactures
weapons and for this
military industrial complex to remain
profitable and viable you need Wars
across the world
so you start wars and then you sell
weapons to both parties or to one party
and that's how you keep profiting
so uh
so the U.S actually uh
it profits from war so I think they will
I'm assuming
they will either engineer more Wars or
they may themselves get involved in wars
in the future
Shaheen says what are the major factors
and causes of the decline of Hinduism in
Southeast Asia now the island of Bali
and some other pockets of the charm
Hindus left in South Vietnam and
Cambodia apart from that there is no
more Hinduism in Southeast Asia the
major course cause of the decline of
Hinduism in eastern Asia was the decline
of India itself
see Hinduism
the birthplace of Dharma
and Hinduism Buddhism all of that the
birthplace is India the Indian
subcontinent right and from the Indian
subcontinent see here's the Indian
subcontinent you can see where it is
it's at the center of Asia it has this
god-gifted position in the center of the
Indian Ocean region and
Hinduism and Indian culture and Dharma
were exported out of India in various
directions starting from the time of
Emperor Ashoka then later Emperor
kanishka also did a lot of this so
Emperor Ashok uh focused on the west to
a certain significant extent he exported
you know Indian culture all the way to
Greece and also to suvarna bhumi and
Lanka and all that so what nabumi was
essentially today's Thailand but it was
kanishka Emperor kanishka who came about
I don't know four or five centuries
later roughly look it up
who exported
Dharma eastwards into China and all the
way eventually it went into Japan
so
the epicenter the the the
heartland of Dharma of Hinduism was the
Indian subcontinent
and it and
when it comes to Southeast Asia Thailand
Vietnam Cambodia allows all that place
all these places Hinduism was exported
to these regions by the great merchants
of Kalinga this started at least 3000
years before today Kalinga is totally
forgotten today when it comes to the
great uh it's it's great influence the
the in enormous influence it has had not
only on India culturally but on much of
the world culturally especially East
Asia Kalinga is today's Orissa when we
talk about is uttarakalinga
so all of that right so the heartland of
Hinduism and Dharma overall is the
Indian subcontinent and all of Southeast
Asia Eastern Asia
was it came under Indian influence
uh whether it is Indonesia all of
Indonesia was Hindu all of Thailand
Cambodia the Southeast Asian regions all
of that was Hindu China and Japan and
Korea and all where Buddhist nominali
but there is a lot of Hindu influence
there also
so all of this was made possible because
of the uh predominance and preeminence
of India culturally and economically and
militarily but Indian culture was never
exported through military means it was
always done through through cultural
diffusion primarily done by Traders and
Merchants
uh so that's how it was so once India
itself declined in the past 1 000 years
because India came under foreign
occupation starting with the Turks and
then the Europeans
once India started declining
the the influence started across the
rest of Asia also started declining
so that's why Hinduism declined in
Southeast Asia there are some Pockets
left where is Bali Bali is here here it
is you see Bali
this here is Bali this island here and
there are some Hindus the charm charm
Hindus
in Vietnam Cambodia Etc
so yeah that's what happened so it was a
decline of India that led led to the
decline of Indian influence and culture
in much of Asia so Indonesia eventually
became Islamic so did Malaysia
and so on so these nations then
eventually went their own way and they
that's what happened so it was the
decline of India that caused this
all right let's see some other questions
um
okay Omar Omar says
would you support a confederation
between India Pakistan Bangladesh what
are the pros and cons of each Nation
umizam from Dhaka Bangladesh host of the
book Cafe podcast
um
it's a good question I would not support
a confederation especially with Pakistan
see the reason for this is the people of
Pakistan are
they are taught to hate India
it's it's a it's something that start
from the day they are born
they have this visceral most I'm not
saying all of the pakistanis I'm sure
there are pakistanis who don't hate
India as well but overall the
majoritarian position is that India is
the number one enemy
this is there is a visceral deep rooted
hatred for India
and Pakistan we know what's happened
over the past three four decades
especially after the Allah came to power
Pakistan has become the world's major
like I said every nation has a major
export the U.S exports War Pakistan
exports terrorism Pakistan is the
world's terrorism epicenter Terror
Central
you simply cannot have a confederation
with open borders let's say with a
nation like that we in India don't want
to have anything to do with Pakistan
Pakistan is an issue that's left over
from history the British created
Pakistan they divided the Indian
subcontinent into all these you know
separate Nations
so it's a temporary situation eventually
Pakistan will disintegrate
it's being propped up by foreign powers
just recently I think yesterday they got
a new IMF bailout
three billion dollars of whatever so
they will not allow Pakistan to fail
because they need Pakistan as a counter
difference to India they need it to keep
on uh keep India off balance
so Pakistan is a hostile Nation
its entire
it's a reason for existing is to counter
balance India and to keep India off
balance and to keep leading and pricking
and bleeding India you can't have a
confederation between India and Pakistan
when it comes to Bangladesh
eventually I think it will happen
uh once again the issue is that there
are lots of bangladeshis also I'm not
saying all Bangladesh there are lots of
wonderful bangladeshis who see India as
as well we are the same eventually
Bangladesh was part of Bengal Bangladesh
from a Mahabharata times so we all are
the same people but once again
there is this issue there are there are
some bangladeshis certain sections of
Bangladesh Society who have a great
hatred for India and who who see more of
a common cause with Pakistan
uh so that's this issue as well these
issues will all overall be resolved with
time it won't happen immediately I think
India and Bangladesh are already
cooperating to a very significant extent
uh that's why the Americans want resume
change in Bangladesh they want to uh you
know
they they want to depose
Ena
the Americans
they are you know they can see signs and
symptoms of that happening so India and
Bangladesh already have excellent
relations
and the relations will only improve over
time
and eventually I have no doubt that the
subcontinent overall entirely will
reunify but it will take maybe a hundred
years it won't happen as far as I can
see during my lifetime or our lifetimes
but let's say by 2100 or 2150 things may
be very different eventually the
subcontinent will reunify and reunite
that's that's gonna happen
so I think it's not something we should
rush into or try to engineer because it
will create problems which we don't want
I think the situation that we have
between India and Bangladesh is already
very good we have Indians who there are
Indians who study in Bangladesh you know
medical colleges and all that and there
are Bangladeshi people who come to India
for studies as well and tourism is there
lots of stuff is there so uh
when it comes to India and Bangladesh I
think the situation is great it will
only keep on improving there are certain
issues that obviously my viewers would
be talking about that there is illegal
immigration and all okay eventually it
will all be resolved because
it will be resolved but Pakistan is a
different issue so Pakistan will have to
disintegrate first which it will
naturally do
uh there are too many centrifugal forces
within Pakistan that are tearing it
apart it's being held together
artificially by the west but it will
eventually break up I think sooner
rather than later and then it will
eventually naturally uh evolve into into
a different kind of kind of a bunch of
Nations and eventually we will be able
to reintegrate it into India so uh pros
and cons for each Nation the con when it
comes to Pakistan is Terrorism and
hatred for India so that's a huge con
when it comes to Bangladesh or India the
cons are less Pros or more eventually so
I think India and Bangladesh could could
have a consideration much before much
before anything like that could happen
with Pakistan
all right
um
authentic historical books about
Napoleon Bonaparte to read uh listen I
am very bad with book recommendations
because I've read so many books I can't
remember the names they are all the
knowledge all the information all the
data that I've absorbed over time
it eventually amalgamates and I don't
have any specific book recommendation to
give what I would suggest is go to
Amazon or Flipkart or whatever you know
their favorite online retailer
search for Napoleon in in the book
section and see which book has the
highest number of four plus star ratings
that would be a good place to start
right uh I have a book or two somewhere
here but I'll not go into that right now
so
there are lots of good books about
Napoleon so yeah do that go to Amazon or
Flipkart or whatever
see the best books lots of Four Star
Plus reviews and that would be a good
place to start and it's It's never
enough to read one book you've got to
read more
at least like three four books to have a
reasonably well-rounded understanding of
a subject
um what do we have what else do we have
um
neighbor whatever the name is okay what
are the chances of Modi winning the next
election I think Modi is still in pole
position to win the next election
obviously there are foreign forces that
don't want this to happen
are primarily in the west but I think
I I would say that the government should
not become complacent
uh like kind of the way the vajpayee
government became complacent a little
bit one would say you know with
reasonable uh accuracy it's you know in
2004 they were very confident they would
win in the law they ended up losing so
that sort of complacency should never
creep in there are lots of challenges
lots of issues you see what's happening
in Manipur
I I would say that it's being fomented
by outside outside external forces
to keep India off balance
so there are gonna be these challenges I
have said this that the breaking India
forces will intensify interactions in
the run-up to the 24 elections they will
try their best to make the Prime
Minister look bad and weak in what's
happening in Manipur is a symptom of
that they want to make the government
look weak
right so um
I I think Mr Modi should win the next
election and I hope he wins
but I hope that the government doesn't
become too complacent they should not
take anything for granted that's what I
would say
all right
um
what else do we have
what else what else what else
M's access do you think Bose could have
persuaded Jinnah away from partition if
he was in India in the 1940s
so there's no persuading somebody Gina
the P who really
crafted
and implemented the partition of India
it wasn't Jinnah it was British they
used Jinnah as an excuse they used him
as a puppet as a prop
they all they always wanted to partition
India that's always been their policy of
the Anglo-Saxon Empire before you leave
a colony you break into pieces
right so they always wanted to partition
India
so Jina was simply an excuse he was in
London he was in England for for a
decade
he came back to India in the 1930s with
a new Zeal in a new objective
so where did it come from they said that
he read mustafa's biography written by
HC Armstrong and that
that could be a cause this could be a
factor which which you gave new zealed
and gave the idea of breaking India and
creating a Pakistan out of it but
overall it was a British who did this
so it was not about persuading if if
somebody would have pursued it just not
to give this up they would have found
somebody else to be the leader the
British they would have found somebody
else to be the leader of the Pakistan
movement so it is the the country was
not partitioned because of one man
he was simply the figurehead of the
partition thing the British partition
India
so if you wanted to stop the partition
of India you had to defeat the British
so we had an opportunity in 1946. when
we had the Indian Naval Rebellion
against the British in Mr Gandhi and Mr
Patel
jinxed it the next it in the bud
you know they made promises they first
of all demoralized
the Indian Naval Sailors and officers
and they made false promises which were
immediately broken
so had the rebellion of 1946 succeeded
it would have succeeded had the Indian
army come to know about it
so it was a matter of time before it
happened so they had to act very fast
and persuade
the Rebels the naval Rebels to give up
to to abandon the Rebellion so in 1946
if that Rebellion had succeeded India
would have never been partitioned
because they would have you know
acquired Freedom through Force
through strength instead of being given
freedom on on British terms on a platter
and what happened was a transfer of R1
from one set of crooks to another set of
crooks so it was not about persuading
Jinnah if you had persuaded Jinnah do
you think partition would not have
happened what nonsense they would have
thrown swept Jinnah aside and found
themselves a new figurehead for the
partition movement
uh so yeah that's the thing
so for partition to not happen either
the 1946 Rebellion should have succeeded
or Bose
or the other situation scenario is that
those would have succeeded in conquering
India from the East which did not happen
so yeah that's the thing
sabana says what do you think about the
Titan submersible so yeah that that
disaster
so which year did the Titanic sink
somewhere in the 1910s something like
that
um and I think more than a thousand
people died in that and then in 2023 I
don't know six more people died in the
same location roughly
so so that was the Titan not the Titanic
the submersible the submarine so what do
I think I think it was a disaster uh it
was not a well-engineered submersible it
had lots of structural issues first of
all its Hull was made of fiberglass
you want something stronger than
fiberglass when you have a submersible
every submarine based on the material
it's made of and the various engineering
characteristics every submarine has
something called a crush depth
it's the depth Beyond it at which the
submarine implodes because of the
pressure of the ocean of the water
so every submarine has a crush depth and
every submarine has an operating depth
below which you should not go it can
still go below that but eventually you
will reach Crush depth at which point
the submarine simply implodes because it
can no longer withstand the pressure of
the ocean
and so if you want to construct a
submarine they can do really deep Dives
then you need to have sufficiently
strong material for the hull and
sufficiently good engineering and
clearly this Titan submission
submersible was deficient in both the
engineering as well as the the strength
of the hull
and they I think they had done a lot of
cost cutting and cutting corners and all
that the guy the the the CEO the owner
of the company he refused to hire
competent Engineers because they were
white apparently I mean what nonsense
doesn't make any sense but that's what
it did and
used very basic equipment like like a I
don't know what a gaming controller to
control the submersible and all that so
there were there was a lot of cost
cutting a lot of cutting Corners a lot
of shortcuts but they can and yeah
eventually we know what happened it
it imploded
so yeah it was an avoidable tragedy but
well that's what it is it's a lesson for
future people future Engineers to learn
okay what else
um
Pawan gaukar says you use the word
greatest Empire the world is ever
witnessed for America whom does but whom
does this Empire serve surely it does
not serve all parts of its Empire no it
serves the people who control the empire
an Empire doesn't serve everybody
let's take the exam on Empire
the Roman Empire controlled the entire
Mediterranean region let's go to the map
so if we look at the Roman Empire
initially it's uh Capital was Rome
and it controlled much of Europe so the
whole of the whole of Iberia which is
today's Spain they had conquered uh the
British Isles
they had conquered goal which is France
much of Germany All the Way East up to
Judea which is present day Israel
Lebanon Syria all that much of presently
turkey Egypt they had conquered and
Northern Africa as well
all right so did the Romans Empire serve
all the people who lived in this region
no
it
exploited these conquered territories
for resources
and the purpose was to enrich Rome
itself
so the people of Rome they had very high
standards of living good quality of life
but even within Rome
it was only the elites
you know who actually enjoyed the fruits
of the Empire truly
so an Empire does not serve everybody
all its subjects
it only serves the elites the Masters
the ones who are truly empowered in the
Empire let's talk about the British
Empire did it serve India it exploited
India it destroyed India totally
did it serve Mesopotamia no he did not
the British Empire didn't serve Africa
much of Africa was conquered by the
British Empire
it did not so Empires typically are
exploitative
in nature
Indian Empires were different because we
never really uh you know
colonized
we had empires in India we had the
Maureen Empire the kushan Empire the
Gupta Empire the karkota Empire the
Chola Empire the marathamp Empire Etc
the Chola has conquered the entirety of
Saudi Syria all the way to the
Philippines but it was not colonization
it was simply conquest and then there
were these nations these kingdoms were
allowed to rule as vasals
so there was no extraction of wealth
when it came to Indian Empires but when
it comes to other Empires Western
Empires whether it was the Roman Empire
or the British Empire or the American
Empire its extraction of wealth
how does the U.S extract wealthy will
ask
they do it through the financial system
the US dollar they take debt the America
the U.S debt to GDP ratios is is
ridiculous
they they have trillions of dollars of
debt which they will never repay
if they if they are asked to repay the
debt they will simply print dollars
because all the all the debt is in U.S
dollars and the Americans can print
dollars anytime they want so essentially
they will only repay the debt in paper
paper money
so you know so America doesn't serve the
world it serves itself and even within
the US it serves whoever really runs the
country clearly not the president
so yeah that's the deal
um
okay
auspicious doomsday says what could be
the Russian plan if it wants to restore
its former superpower position
how could Russia engineer problems with
the US and how will U.S vasals Suffer
Well that's a very wide-ranging
expansive question you asked but it's a
good question so obviously Russia would
like to restore it's it's
its former superpower position and
Russia has great advantages it has in
enormous territory right it looks
enormous on this map but it's it's quite
large for sure
uh
so Russia is essentially an otaki it is
self-sufficient in all the basic needs
that a nation would have agriculture
Russia is self-sufficient minerals
Russia is unsufficient oil and gas
Russia has everything it needs all the
Rare Earth Resources whatever you need
you know for for a fully industrialized
Nation all the resources are available
within Russia itself so it is an old
arcade is not dependent on anybody else
it does not depend on other nations for
oil or gas or or metals or coal or
anything or agriculture anything at all
so that's the great Advantage Russia has
and eventually they would want to well
if it wants to become a superpower again
it has to become a great economy again
it already has a huge military and the
world's largest arsenal of nuclear
weapons
um how could Russia engineer problems
for the US well it could expand its
footprint in Europe for starters
so your credit could eventually overtake
Maybe
you know the former Warsaw Pact Nations
is the Eastern European nations
eventually could come under Russian's
way if they are able to engineer that
and then once that happens other nations
would you know if if they are able to
bring Nations out of the U.S orbit that
would that would cause a great uh
uh decline in the U.S Prestige and
credibility which is something that
would engineer problems with the US
throughout the world and when it comes
to Africa also Russia provides security
and safety to various African regimes
through the Wagner forces for instance
and all that then if Russia as part of
brics could uh you know succeed in
creating a new brics currency and
creating a separate world order the
cigarette a separate economic and
financial order that could also create
huge problems for the US so it's
something that will happen over time
they will certainly try to do this and
the Americans will try to try their best
to resist this so that's a tug of war we
are witnessing in real time right now in
the 2020s and by the time 2030 comes
around I think the world could be a very
different place from what it is right
now
um
this is a question I get a lot what do I
think about end rotate I don't know much
about him I have not I I think uh lots
of people uh are very greatly influenced
by him for some reason I think he had a
lot of videos on the internet and all
that I have not seen a single video of
his I don't really know what he stands
for I don't know why he is so famous and
popular and all that and there are lots
of controversies around him you know
uh he was arrested I suppose in Romania
I'm not sure if he's still under arrest
he and his brother so I don't know
I really haven't spent any time trying
to research this in this gentleman and
understand his life history and why he's
so famous I've never been interested so
I don't know it's a question I get all
the time so let me answer this right now
I don't know much about Android
okay what else
which country is the biggest threat to
India in the long run China or the US
uh well you know geographically China is
next door they have conquered Tibet in
the 1950s and now we have a common
border with China a very long extensive
border which is completely undemarkated
the Chinese have refused to demarcate
the Border they want to keep this issue
open so that they can keep India off
balance they can keep on needling India
keep on pricking and pushing India
salami slicing all that stuff so that's
a huge issue for India
and for India to resolve the China issue
we will have to resolve the Tibet issue
which means Tibet needs to be free again
Tibet needs to be liberated from the
Chinese and it's nowhere near happening
right now we are not in a position to do
that right now maybe in the next 20
years we may be in a position to perhaps
do something about it so China is a
long-term threat for us
China is a long-term threat the
significant real and present danger for
India China and why is China a threat
it's because India is the only nation in
Asia that is that can pose a challenge
to China
India is the only nation in Asia
that can you know
possibly in the long run compete with
China and surpass China
historically India has always been the
world's largest economy
until the 17 1700s
and China was always number two
historically
we'll look up Angus Madison's research
so that's the potential that India has
that's been his India's historic
rightful position at the top of the
global economic chain the world's
largest economy so China knows India's
potential and they've grabbed a lot of
territory and all that right now they've
become so large inflated but India has
this potential
so that's why the Chinese fear India
they fear India
and that's why China is a huge threat
right now China is way more powerful the
economy is about
what's India's economic uh GDP right now
3.7 trillion dollars or something China
is about 16 17 something around that so
it's way larger and because of that it
has a much more powerful military but
it's tied out it's tied up in various
places because they have
started conflicts with everybody
so so China is a real and present
present threat for India in the long run
the U.S
the US also now sees India as a
long-term threat a long-term competitor
a long-term rival
India is emerging
India has is finally getting its act
together
in the Indian economy is finally growing
and it's projected to keep growing for
the next 20 years at least
So eventually India could become the
next China that's a possibility it's a
possibility that the Americans will not
discount so that's why they see India as
a long-term rival and they will do their
best to not allow this to happen
how do you do it you keep India under
pressure by creating issues within India
you can start you know
like what's happening in Manipur right
now
that's an example what happened when
Donald Trump visited in India what
happened at the time I think we cannot
remember what was going on in India at
the time
uh they can create a color Revolution
kind of situation that's something they
have perfected over time
they can destabilize India's
neighborhood
you know we know what's happening in
Nepal large-scale Christian conversions
we know what's happening in the other
parts of the subcontinent
um and so on so so the US is also a huge
threat for India they don't want India
to rise they want India to be off
balance they want India to be only
sufficiently strong enough
to counterbalance China but not more
than that so they will cooperate with
India in certain ways but they will also
work against India in a lot of ways they
will keep demonizing India about you
know that that fake Boogie of Human
Rights and democracy and all that which
the Americans pull out anytime they need
to pressurize the nation
so they will keep on doing that so I
think both Nations
are a threat to India in the long run I
have nothing against either Nation
actually
I would like to see both Nations do well
but
facts are facts they both see India as
uh as a rival
and they will do their best the Chinese
would like India to eventually break up
into pieces and so would the Americans
actually
and they indulge in what they call
subnational diplomacy you know and they
they they fund various anti-india forces
the Americans do the Chinese also do
that so it's an issue it's a huge
problem for India and the only solution
for India is to keep Rising keep rising
and rise over the next 20 years do not
get involved in any major military
conflict keep Rising grow the economy
and once the economy is at a certain
certain place like let's say around 10
trillion dollars then we will be able to
resist lots of these external forces and
then we'll be able to solve internal
problems which we are not able to solve
right now
so that's the situation India is in I
think both Nations
are long-term adversaries actually for
India so we
try our best
to maintain good relations over our
prime minister recently very recently
was in the U.S and he was given a very
good welcome very warm welcome
and both Nations both leaders Mr Modi
and Mr Biden spoke about what India and
America have in common democracy and all
those shared values or whatever it is
and all that this is the age of AI
America and India all that so India will
try its best to cooperate with the US
and also with China in whatever way we
can but overall we have to be realistic
that both Nations see India as an
adversary in the long run so India is
going to have to walk the tightrope do
the tightrope walking act and hopefully
we do it right
which for which we will need the right
leadership
so if India votes the wrong
leadership into power
it's game over essentially
okay
um
what else
says support feminism feminists talk
about equal rights but not about taking
responsibility Dharma teaches about
performing duties it doesn't feminism
lead to the emasculation of men you know
feminism is a foreign concept it's a
newfangled concept that came out of the
West it emerged out of the west west
because of the defects and deficiencies
and horrors of Western Society women
were horribly
down Jordan
in the West
so feminism it's a whole history you
know I'll not go into the details but
first I think emerge out of the U.S
so over there in Western Society because
of
the cultural values and all that you
know the Catholic Christian values or
whatever because of that women were
second-class citizens they were very
badly doubt Road and they had no rights
until the mid 20th century women did not
have the the right to vote in many
nations in Europe
I think until the beginning until the
1990s I think there were certain parts
of Switzerland where women could not
vote they did not have the right to vote
so that's the kind of society the West
is
so that's why feminism came out of
necessity it arose out of necessity they
had to do some women to do something
about this
um to get the same rights as men
so then feminism emerged that's the
emergence of feminism and then feminism
kind of became the dominant ideology and
now it it what uh this the comment says
over here the emasculation of men it's
true so now what's happening is that
this feminism has merged with the woke
ideology and all that
and what we are seeing now in the west
is that men are becoming feminine and
women are becoming masculine
and it is men who are now the oppressed
gender
that's the weirdness that's happened in
the west when it comes to sanatan Dharma
there is no concept of feminism and
there is no concept of equal rights
it's about
diff I mean
in in Dharma we don't really talk about
rights we talk about responsibilities
but Dharma has always treated women
extraordinarily well
you know women actually have a more
exalted status than men in in a in many
ways
so
you know we have to understand that this
concept of equality is is wrong
there is no equality in nature there is
no equality anywhere in the world
right you cannot equate a man with a
woman
these two genders play different roles
and now they'll say why are you talking
about gender rules because that's that's
the truth that's always been
the fact in human history
thousands of years tens of thousands of
years hundreds of thousands of years of
human human evolution males and females
played different roles
now we have technology and the human
male Brown and Brown and muscle power is
not really required we I agree so today
gender roles and all that is are
naturally changing even in India we have
the induction of women into the Armed
Forces
yeah
um
so uh that's just how things are
changing and a lot of it a lot of it is
because of Western influence but yes
feminism leads to the emasculation of
men
and today the thing is in the Indian
education system especially in colleges
and universities they teach what what do
they call gender studies or whatever it
is
and feminism is taught so women so girls
are made to feel like you know they have
been oppressed for thousands of years
throughout history that was true in the
west but not in the east
but that's what they're taught so then
this concept of feminism also has
emerged in in India and women want to be
like you know the way the Western women
are the stronger the more dominant
gender and all that so it's it's a mess
I I hope too much of this doesn't get
introduced into India the education
system is mainly to blame and also the
entertainment industry
so uh so when it comes to sanatan Dharma
there was never any oppression of women
and women actually had a very highly
respected and rather exalted position
in society
okay
um
Rahul says I see a massive amount of
hatred Prejudice ridiculed from
Europeans and Americans about India
plenty of dehumanization why do they
have a track record of being so
shockingly hateful see Europe has always
been racist America is nothing but an
outcome than a new colony of Europe
settler settler colonization
and all of this goes back to the
Catholic Church the pope so when uh
Christopher Colombo discovered this new
land he thought it was India it was
actually the Americas
um the pope gave the right to the
um
to the to the Explorers
to claim any territory as their own as
long as they did not have Christians
so if so the this thing was created that
if a person if if a society is not a
Christian Society it is subhuman it is
inferior and it can be enslaved and
destroyed and that's what actually
happened and that's what colonialism was
um
so that's something that's part of their
culture it's part of their history the
Europeans and the Americans are nothing
but you know settler European settlers
who have settled who settled on in this
new continent after destroying
the natives this horrific genocide of
the Native Americans happened at least
at least 50 to 100 million
individuals people innocent people were
killed by the Europeans
uh so now what we see
is that the West is no longer the
predominant force in the world it is
still the richest uh block so to say in
the world the so-called first world the
global North so to say
they are still the richest but now the
East is emerging especially China and
India they don't see Russia as part of
the West so Russia itself now is part of
the East so the East is emerging and the
three major pools are Ric Russia India
China
and obviously when a dominant power sees
new powers emerging they are jealous and
resentful
and that's why they will try to
demoralize this new emerging Powers by
making them feel inferior which is why
you see all this ridicule this prejudice
is hatred and the dehumanization so it's
actually a symptom when it comes to
India of India's
emergence as a new power in the world
it's a new economy a major economy and a
major geopolitical Force which has
happened very rapidly after the Ukraine
war
so because India is now emerging
and India is no longer uh
you know
subsidiary or or uh
you know dominated by the West that's
why you are seeing this jealousy this
hatred in this Prejudice and this is
ridicule and the humanization
which is a symptom of their helplessness
in the face of India's uh rise India is
beginning to rise now India is
essentially where the Chinese were in
the 19 late 1980s early 1990s that's
where India is at now it's just early
days
India has at least two decades of very
hard intense work in front of it for
India to be where China is today at
least 20 years
so Indian should not get complacent that
we are rising we are now vishwa Guru we
are super power no no no we are
beginning to learn how to walk
remember that and the world notices this
the world now notices that India is
becoming more confident in India is
actually now Rising
so that's why they don't like it and
that's why we see this attitude and this
entire thing of racial hatred racism all
that it's part of European culture it's
part of the European DNA
so
not not surprising to see all this
aparna says what's your analysis of the
Wagner group revolved in Russia what
does it tell about Russia's Internal
Affairs I have an entire video about
this which came out two three days ago
take a look at that but if you want me
to answer right now in brief it was a
psychological operation it was not a
coup at all
it was a redeployment in broad daylight
essentially
off the Wagner forces from Ukraine
to Belarus let's take a look at the map
so let's go to Ukraine we know what it
is so the Wagner forces were in
the dunbas region which is
uh
eastern Ukraine right
and they fought the Battle of bhagmud
which is here which is now called
artemovsk
so they fought the Battle of Bahamut and
it took it lasted 224 days and
eventually after 2-24 days Wagner the
Wagner forces were able to win the city
of Bahamut at the cost of an enormous
amount of Ukrainian
lives and material
so now Wagner wanted to
so now the Russians wanted to redeploy
Wagner from the donbass region into
Belarus so recently Belarus so Belarus
essentially is a Russian Ally you could
you would not be mistaken to call it a
Russian vasal State all right
and recently just a month or so ago in
the past month or two Russia has
transferred tactical nuclear weapons to
Belarus territory so Belarus now hosts
on its territory tactical nuclear
weapons that belong to Russia
so you can see the close
interconnectedness that Russia and
Belarus have Belarus is Right North
absolutely north of Ukraine
and with the Belarus border is about a
hundred kilometers or so
maybe less from the Ukrainian capital of
Kiev
so what the Russians wanted to do was
they wanted to redeploy the Wagner
forces that had done their job in in
successfully in the dharmas region they
wanted to redeploy them in Belarus all
the way
so they did this in broad daylight by
creating an artificial fake coup
so you know you have any precaution the
boss of Wagner has done this in the past
on May in the beginning of May this year
he claimed that Wagner was retreating
and withdrawing from bhagmud because the
Russian military under uh segregation
and uh and the other guy grasemov they
were starving Wagner of ammunition
so he said we are withdrawing but they
did not withdraw and they won the battle
so it was it was a psychological
operation they fooled the West in in
Europe and the world into believing that
there was
there was descent
within Russia within the Russian forces
and there was a rebellion and that Putin
had apparently lost control of what was
happening but there was that was not the
case
so now this was an even bigger
psychological operation or even bigger
deception that Wagner did they pretended
to create to start a coup
right and they marched towards Moscow
they took the city of rostov on Don
yeah they captured the city then they
marched northwards towards Moscow there
were 200 kilometers from Moscow
and then
they said no we are no longer doing we
are we are abandoning the coup and then
the very rapidly deployed westwards and
entered Belarus and right now isn't is
in essentially apparently Minsk and
Wagner forces are in Belarus
So within 24 hours the coup was over in
Wagner had been redeployed from bakmut
from from the donbass region all the way
into Belarus with the Western media and
the Western governments cheering for
them
so that's what happened
in broad daylight in full view of the
world this is what happened so it was a
psychological operation and what it also
did is that it kind of exposed the
traitors within Russia the ones who
supported the coup the fake coup but the
deal is this was not a coup anybody who
has seriously studied how a coup is
executed will know it's not a coup study
the book
by Edward Luther that's the book you
need to study if you want to understand
how to execute a coup which I would not
recommend executing a coup but I would
recommend studying the book
so this was a fake coup and it has
actually made Vladimir Putin stronger
and exposed his enemies
that's what it did
okay
uh what else do we have
um lots of questions
the events for the next 15 days I cannot
I have no idea what's going to happen
tomorrow or the next 15 days that's not
what I do I am not there are certain
so-called geopolitical experts who say
every one of my predictions come right
comes right
you know they they have made they have
created a name for themselves by
claiming that they always make accurate
predictions you know no geopolitical
analyst can make 100 accurate
predictions you will always get
something wrong
so I am not in the business of
predicting events
I analyze what's happening and I can
give possible scenarios of what could
happen
but I cannot predict what's actually
going to happen I can always get things
wrong I think everybody gets things
wrong
I don't think it was fakes they're all
right Amnesia it's up to you to believe
what you want to believe
entirely your your choice
so so if this was not a fake who then
what what was the outcome of the coup
so precaution went through Russian
territory for hundreds of kilometers he
was not stopped he was not arrested when
he could have been arrested the he was
given unimpeded access
you know on the M4 Highway for hundreds
of kilometers he was allowed to go into
Belarus
and
what was the outcome of the coup if you
don't think it was fake
if it was a real coup Putin would have
crushed them
he has the military power to crush any
Rebel any Rebellion he chose not to
anyway it's up to you what to believe I
can give you my analysis when you can
make your own decisions and
understanding based on that right that's
fine I respect your opinion I respect
your right to have a different opinion
based on your understanding of how
things have gone
how far behind are we in jet engine
technology will we be able ever be able
to pull it off see the one stumbling
block when it comes to jet engines so we
have to understand how jet engines work
there are various different kinds of jet
engines let's talk about the standard
turbo fan engine engine that we have
that is used in fighter jets fighter
aircraft
so inside a jet engine what happens is
you suck in air from outside
you mix it with fuel
you ignite it and that ignition is
essentially results in an explosion that
you control
and that expels gases out
from the outlet behind the Jet Engine
and that's what impels that what's
provide that what that is what provides
the
the impulse that that uh that powers the
aircraft the the jet so that's what
propels the aircraft forward
so you suck in air from from from from
ahead from uh from let's say this is a
jet engine this is the inlet so air will
be sucked in from here and inside there
will be in English and it will be mixed
with the jet with the jet fuel it will
be ignited and there's a whole you know
there are the turbine blades and all
that which will Spin and the
uh exhaust will be ejected from behind
and that's what propels the uh jet
engine in there cut forward so inside
the engine you have incredibly high
temperatures
1500 2000 degrees Celsius I'm not sure
exactly what the temperature is you can
look it up if you want but we have
extremely high temperatures temperatures
be a in the temperatures are higher than
the melting point of Iron and Steel and
many metals
so then the question is if the
temperatures are so high for a jet
engine to have a certain amount of
thrust which you need
trust is measured in kilonewtons when it
comes to jet engines right so if you
want a certain amount of thrust you will
have a you will need a certain amount of
certain temperature inside the Jet
Engine and this temperature is
higher than the melting point of your
standard metals like steel and all that
so then of what material do you make
your turbine blades your turbine blades
have to be able to withstand those
temperatures for a sustained amount of
time and not only for one Mission but
for a few hundred missions for let's say
at least 100 Missions
so what material will you make that
turbine blade out of
so that is the Crux that's where we are
behind we have not invested in Material
Science so when it comes to let's say
that the General Electric uh F whatever
engine it is the the turbine blade is
made out of a single Crystal of a
certain metallic alloy a single Crystal
you don't take molten metallic alloy and
you cast it and you make turbine place
out of it you don't do that you grow the
entire turbine blade out of a single
Crystal of that metal metallic alloy and
that is a very specialized specific
technology India has not been able to
develop it thus far because it's
extremely it takes a lot of time to
develop it lots of trial and error you
have to try and fail several hundred
times to get it right
so we don't have the infrastructure we
don't have the researchers
I think we have a jet engine
uh
research establishment somewhere in
Bangalore or something I'm not sure they
have been trying to develop the the what
is it called the kaveri engine and the
Cavalry engine gives a certain amount of
thrust which is insufficient for what we
need
I think the trust the thrust it gives is
about 50 60 maybe 70 kilo newtons I
don't think it's up to 70. so it's in
it's enough to power drones and all that
but not enough to power a fighter jet
so I think the Aegis fighter jet needs
at least 110 120 kilo newtons of thrust
if I am not mistaken if I'm not mistaken
I don't know the numbers in front of me
right now but yeah so for that you need
an engine which can generate a very high
temperature higher than what it is but
we don't have the
um
ability to to
to create turbine blades that can
withstand those temperatures so the
crucial technology that we are missing
is the turbine blade technology how to
build turbine blades that can that can
withstand those incredibly high
temperatures so that's done by build by
growing the entire blade out of a single
Crystal of a specific metallic alloy
which contains nickel and certain other
metals if I am not mistaken and that's
what we have not been able to do because
we have not invested in Material Science
research
that's why we are far behind eventually
we'll be able to do it I'm not sure what
the status is right now maybe it's
classified
maybe it's secret you know we don't
reveal these this information to the
public so I am not sure where we are in
the development of an indigenous jet
engine right now we have signed a
memorandum of agreement with uh General
Electric I think of the US
in which they will transfer certain
number certain
a certain amount of jet engine
technology to India and these engines
will be built in India which is which is
a good start and some people say it's
about 80 percent of the technology which
should be transferred way that remains
to be seen it's just a memorandum
memorandum of understanding that's been
signed thus far uh so we will have to
see how much technology we actually get
but we will certainly not be given the
crucial technology
the uh single Crystal turbine blade
technology that is something we will
have to find a way to develop on our own
so that's the issue we will eventually
be able to pull it off it will take time
maybe 10 years maybe 20 years
you know optimistically maybe less but
realistically maybe 10 20 years
okay what else do we have we have so
many many questions uh Elliot Anderson
says when will India have its own Google
Facebook YouTube Instagram that is
global and animation gaming Kpop like
Industries
uh you know there is only so much the
government can do when it comes to
Google Facebook YouTube Instagram
animation whatever these are all Private
Industry private companies
the US government has nothing to do with
this
you can't expect the government to go
and solve every problem the country has
the private sector needs to step in
so to develop something like Google or
Facebook YouTube you need to take risks
right it takes a lot of money
to build such a company and we have very
rich people in India but unfortunately I
think the the culture of taking big
risks still isn't there because of I
mean for obvious reasons India for the
past 1000 years has been under foreign
occupation people have been artificially
impoverished by the British
there is so much poverty in India even
today which is all something that stems
back to the British times when the
British disenfranchise the Indian people
and stole all the land and read this
distributed to their minions
so today that's that's the issue so
Indians became very risk hours
in the past two 300 years maybe a
thousand years
so that that attitude needs to change it
will take time right so so Indian
business people they want to invest
their money in in Ventures that have
lower risk rather than high risk
Ventures and that's why India is not you
know coming up with these
uh you know Googles and Facebooks and
all that
so I think it can happen in the next
five ten years if if people who are
sufficiently wealthy would take
risks
okay uh lots of other questions as
always let's see what else do we have
um
why is the Super Chat option not
appearing in Mac OS only super stickers
it won't appear in Android also or in
Windows because I've turned off the
Super Chat option uh I think it is
obscene to
answer questions in exchange for money
and this is not what that's not what the
channel is about I had tried the Super
Chat option a few times initially you
know I turned it on but then what
happened is that some people see when
you do a super chat it's very noticeable
it's very visible so me when I'm looking
at the live chat my eyes will be don't
do that so then I'll end up answering
more questions of those who are paying
to ask questions and there are lots of
students on this channel who watch the
channel and students are broke they have
no money and they are not in a position
to put super chats
so I think it's just wrong to divide my
audience between those who can pay and
those who can't pay so that's why I've
completely Switched Off the Super Chat
option I will treat everybody the same
and I will not take money
for answer for answering questions which
is so stupid
so that's why it's not there it's by
design that it's not there
okay
back his talks are genuine what is Jai
Shankar policy I too didn't understand
actually you know I I would be very
happy and I will certainly bring it back
in a few months
um whenever I go to Delhi next I will be
very happy to bring him back for another
long discussion it's always fun to talk
to him
um when it comes to the Jai Shankar
Doctrine I disagree with with what he
says see I when I have a guest on a
podcast I will never interrupt the guest
and I will never argue with the guest
and I will never disagree with the guest
but those who watch me and those who
follow me and those who watch this
channel regularly will know what my
my positions are
right so when I invite somebody for a
podcast I want to learn I will first of
all invite only those people that I find
interesting and who have something to
offer from whom I can actually learn
something and I want to understand their
position and their perspective so I give
them as much time as they want to say
whatever they want to say and I don't
disagree with them but here I will say
that I don't agree with the with with
his contention that the Jai Shankar
policy is is a flop or there is no
Shankar Doctrine there is a Jai Shankar
Doctrine which is actually actually the
movie Doctrine and which is being
implemented by Dr Jason I think it's a
very successful
Doctrine it's a very successful approach
thus far to geopolitics to India's
unique position in the world it's
tailor-made for that and it's designed
to take India forward so I so
did not agree with that so that's fine
so I have a different position
from from what his position is
so that's something only those who watch
this channel regularly will understand I
actually am very happy with the uh
geopolitical position that India has
taken
is a little more pessimistic when it
comes to that obviously he he obviously
also wants India to do very well but he
has a different different way maybe a
different uh
uh he wants it to be done maybe in a
different way maybe he thinks it is not
being done well enough or strongly
enough and that's so that's okay it's
perfectly fine to have different
opinions
okay
juicer pedifier says do you think
do you think men and women can be
platonic friends roommates I ask between
because science is men and women are
different in every way
P.S I am being a SIM for asking okay um
can men and women be platonic friends I
think it depends on the person
roommates I think it depends I think
some people are incapable of having that
sort of a platonic relationship I think
I think some people can have it
uh dear men and women are very
definitely very different in every way
that's for sure
but once again it all comes down to the
individual so there are certain people
who would be able to have a platonic
relationship with a roommate of the
opposite gender and some people may not
be able to have it so I think it all
depends on the individual
you know
so yeah I don't that's my very simple
straightforward perspective on this it
depends on the person some people can do
it some people can't irrespective of
gender
um
okay what else what else what else uh
lots of questions other questions okay
this is a speculative question what
would happen if Sardar Patel was the
first beer of India instead of nehru
I've answered this question maybe 78
times now I think India would have taken
a different course Mr Patel died soon
after India's the transfer of power in
1947. so maybe who he would not have
been a long lasting prime minister of
India but he would most likely have
prevented China from
from conquering Tibet and maybe the
Indian foreign policy would have been
much more pragmatic much more realistic
instead of being idealistic and stupid
so yeah that's what I could say in short
and India's in the path India would have
taken would have been significantly
different from what it eventually took
okay okay what else
um let's see lots of other questions
warp secretion says I'm a lawyer what
can I do for India I think you what you
can do for India is you excel at your
profession
you do the best possible
job you can on a daily basis in your
profession that's what you can do for
India we want we need people who have
high standards so whether you are a
lawyer whether you're a business person
whether you're a policeman or
policewoman whether you're a soldier
whether you are whatever whether you're
a teacher
do the best you can in your profession
on a daily basis raise your standards
that's what you can do for India if
everybody does that just imagine how
better India will become so that's what
you can do for India
raise your standards do the best you can
rise to the fullest extent of your
potential work consciously towards doing
that if each individual does this India
will be totally transformed so that's
what you can do for India
okay let's take a couple more questions
we have already reached almost two hours
wow
um
uh what else what else
ah controversy shall we go into
controversial matters Dunmore says
what's your view on same sex marriage in
India I think it is totally wrong to
criminalize homosexuality
you know so we have decriminal
decriminalized homosexuality it is the
Narendra Modi government that did that
the Congress and other governments were
in power for decades they did not do it
they they criminalized they were happy
to criminalize homosexuality it was the
Narendra Modi government that
decriminalized homosexuality so that is
something that needed to be done and
we've done that but if you look at human
history
human history that we know of is about
10 000 years
marriage has always been between men and
women
so I think we should give the homosexual
people
the same rights when it comes to them
not being criminalized or or or or
oppressed in any way when it comes to
marriage I think the purpose of marriage
is to be it's the foundation of society
it's to traditionally it's it's to
procreate and all that and obviously
homosexuals cannot procreate so I think
we
we don't have to emulate the West in
everything it does the West is not a
good role model for the world which we
are seeing very well when it comes to
Europe and the us so I think we have our
own culture
to draw
to to fall back upon we have our own way
of life we are the world's oldest and
greatest civilization the world was
civilized by us to a large extent so we
don't need to look at the West for
guidance
we only have to look back at upon at our
own history and traditions
so from that perspective I don't think
we need same-sex marriage in India we
have done a very good thing by
decriminalizing homosexuality they can
live their own life any way they want we
don't care
it doesn't bother us they can do
whatever they want but I think I don't
think marriage is required
you know and I'm sure lots of people
will disagree with me which is fine
but I don't think there's any need for
or maybe if they could there could be
some category or whatever of them having
I I don't know you know as far as I'm
concerned I don't think there's any need
for same-sex marriage in India
decriminalization I think is is good
enough which was unnecessary action
okay
um
rare monsters I'm bisexual I don't
believe in marriage at all be it between
straight people or cured people well
that's fine you can believe you have the
right to believe to hold on to your own
beliefs which is fine
don't get married it's fine no one knows
no one's forcing anybody to either do it
this way or that way but yeah totally
fine
um
laughs
Shaheen says what's the future of Israel
in the next decade what are the major
projects ifro should work on when it
comes to remaining the top three in the
Space Race So Right Now who are the top
three NASA is a big deal
SpaceX is bigger it has a bigger
operation than most Nations a private
company the Chinese space program is
they have dozens of launches every year
the French have lots of launches every
year so I think Israel is not even in
the top five right now not even the top
six perhaps
and Israel is capable of being in the
top three for sure but it needs funding
how many Rockets do we launch every year
how many Rockets did ISRO launch in 2022
I don't think it was even 10. you know
so it's a lack of ambition
in on the part of those who control and
fund Israel which is the Indian
government
the scientists can do the engineers can
do whatever we ask them to do you know
which is what is isro's most powerful
rocket it is the GS building Mark III
which is which is a new name these days
it's been rebranded but it's the GSW
Mark III it is a medium to Light Lift
vehicle
you know there are there are rockets
that are like 10 times 100 times more
powerful than the GSW Mark III
and we are capable of building a rocket
that's easily 10 times more powerful
but I don't know when it's going to
happen
you need funding for that you need to go
ahead from the leadership for that so I
think ISRO is being constrained by a
lack of ambition on the part of the
Indian government
so I don't know what the future is we're
gonna have the chandrayaan 3 next month
no this month this month in a couple of
weeks in round three then we're gonna
have gaganyan at some point in time
maybe in 24 maybe in 25 which is the
human space flight program
which again is like a technology
demonstrator but what next what's the
long-term plan we don't know what the
long-term plan or long-term vision is
I'm not sure the in government even has
a long-term vision for Indian for the
Indian space exploration program the
Chinese have a very clear vision of
where they want to be in 2050 and where
they want to be in 2100
they have a very clear Vision we don't
have a vision so I find this extremely
disappointing
so I don't know what the future is will
we even have a rocket that's 10 times
more powerful in the in the next 10
years I'm not sure about that also
so yeah so the major projects like you
say one is one is which is a mission to
Venus but then what
it has to be part of an integrated
long-term Vision which we don't seem to
have so we are not in the top three in
the space range I'm not sure if we are
definitely not even in the top five in
the top in the Space Race somewhere in
the top ten in the in the you know
bottom of the top 10 that's where we are
which is very disappointing they could
be in the top three or top two actually
if we were to fund ISRO properly anyhow
that's one of the disappointing things
but there are many good things also in
India so yeah
I guess I guess we can't have it all
um
okay what else do we have let me take
one more question perhaps because we
have now crossed the two over limit we
can't do it forever
um
um let's see let's see let me take one
more question one more question
uh
[Laughter]
okay says what's your take on the North
Korean defected yonmi Parks yummy Park
and what she says about food crisis in
North Korea is it really that bad well I
don't know what the truth is in North
Korea I don't have sufficient data I
haven't been there and even if I were to
go there I'm sure I would only see some
the good parts of North Korea there may
be some bad parts which I will not be
able to see so I can't say for sure
um
I have seen a few of our interviews some
parts of that I am not quite sure if she
is very credible you know she's become
kind of a celebrity in the US and she
enjoys that she enjoys that tension and
she wants to stay relevant so I it it I
get the feeling she she every time she
talks she makes the story a little more
outlandish a little more extreme I get
the feeling I'm not sure if I'm right
but that's the feeling I get you know uh
so I am not sure how credible she is
it's one person's account that we are
hearing I'm sure some of it is true I'm
not sure all of it is true so we've got
to be careful in what we believe
actually that's what I'm saying you know
right that's about
me park the North Korean Defector
um should I take one more question
uh
okay
okay I guess I guess we are we are at
the end of
today's session so yeah I'm gonna I'm
gonna end it over here I can see lots of
people are still asking me questions I'm
so sorry but I am gonna have to stop it
here I always try to take as many
questions as possible so let's end it
over here tomorrow I have a live stream
in Hindi so I've not done that for a
long time so lots of people I get this
this request all the time please do a
live stream in Hindi do videos in Hindi
so I'm gonna try to do a live stream in
Hindi tomorrow let's see how well it
goes same time tomorrow 9 pm India time
on the Hindi Channel which is linked in
the in this YouTube channel okay so in
case you want to see me speak Hindi and
answer your questions in Hindi join
tomorrow's live stream at 9 00 PM until
then take care thank you very much
everyone for watching and like I always
say keep raising your standards thank
you I'll see you very soon bye